<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 https://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
      version="3.4">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Species-specific spatial structure, species coexistence and mortality
                pattern in natural, uneven-aged Scots pine (Pinus sylvestris L.)-dominated
                forest</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" usage="primary">
      <namePart type="given">Janusz</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Szmyt</namePart>
      <displayForm>Szmyt, Janusz</displayForm>
      <affiliation>Department of Silviculture, Faculty of Forestry, Poznan University of
                Life Sciences, Wojska Polskiego 69, 60-625, Poznan, Poland.
                jszmyt@up.poznan.pl</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="given">Stefan</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Tarasiuk</namePart>
      <displayForm>Tarasiuk, Stefan</displayForm>
      <affiliation>Department of Silviculture, Warsaw University of Life Sciences-SGGW,
                Nowoursynowska 159, 02-776, Warsaw, Poland</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <originInfo>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2018-02</dateIssued>
      <issuance>continuing</issuance>
      <language>
         <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      </language>
      <physicalDescription>
         <extent>p. 1-16.</extent>
      </physicalDescription>
      <abstract>Complexity of uneven-aged forests results from the heterogeneity of
                their structure reflected among others by the spatial pattern of their components.
                Forest structure is usually modified by various processes operating at different
                scales and time. Structure and processes are not independent, and both are important
                drivers of forest dynamics. The impact of natural processes on forest structure
                manifested in the specific spatial pattern of trees can be quantified by point
                pattern analysis applied to long-term repeatedly measured stem-mapped plots. Such
                studies are relatively scarce in the literature although they provide better insight
                into the mechanisms affecting forest dynamics. Our study is focused on the
                spatiotemporal analysis of the structure of mixed uneven-aged Scots pine-dominated
                forest located at the Kampinoski National Park (Poland). Univariate analysis showed
                that the initial pattern of all live trees was initially random and it shifted
                toward more uniform with forest aging. Spatial patterns of individual tree species
                varied from that stated for all forest community. We observed changes in spatial
                pattern of Scots pine and common oak from random toward more clumped (pine) or
                uniform (oak) pattern. In case of black alder and common birch, the initial
                aggregated pattern was maintained over the examined 14-year period of the forest
                succession. Bivariate analysis showed that the most common interspecific association
                between pairs of tree species was spatial segregation (pine vs. alder, alder vs.
                birch and oak vs. birch) followed by spatial independence (pine vs. oak and oak vs.
                alder). The positive association was stated only for pine and birch and only for
                certain spatial scales (&gt; 5 m). Simultaneously, at small distances they showed
                reciprocal repulsion. Changes in spatial relationships between tree species were
                negligible over 14-year period of forest succession. Our results confirmed the
                density-dependent mortality process in the uneven-aged Scots pine-dominated forest
                over 14-year period of forest development. Our study showed that spatial
                interactions between individuals along with species-specific ecological requirements
                should be incorporated into realistic models of forest development, helping to
                manage the forest ecosystems toward their greater structural complexity.</abstract>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Alnus glutinosa</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Betula</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Pinus sylvestris</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Quercus</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>bivariate analysis</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forest dynamics</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forest ecosystems</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forest succession</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forests</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>models</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>mortality</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>national parks</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>trees</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <geographic>Poland</geographic>
      </subject>
      <location>
         <url displayLabel="Available from publisher's site" usage="primary">https://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10342-017-1084-x</url>
      </location>
      <relatedItem type="host">
         <titleInfo>
            <title>European journal of forest research</title>
         </titleInfo>
         <originInfo>
            <publisher>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher>
         </originInfo>
         <identifier type="issn">1612-4669</identifier>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl3870054</identifier>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl3870054</identifier>
         <part>
            <text>2018 Feb., v. 137, no. 1 p.1-16</text>
         </part>
      </relatedItem>
      <identifier type="doi">10.1007/s10342-017-1084-x</identifier>
      <identifier type="control">9916295558607426</identifier>
      <identifier type="agricola">IND605951161</identifier>
      <extension>
         <identifier type="local">agid:5951161</identifier>
      </extension>
      <recordInfo>
         <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">AGL</recordContentSource>
         <recordCreationDate encoding="marc">180619</recordCreationDate>
         <recordChangeDate encoding="iso8601">20221118103100.0</recordChangeDate>
         <recordIdentifier>9916295558607426</recordIdentifier>
         <recordOrigin>Converted from MARCXML to MODS version 3.4 using NAL-RDAmarc21slim2mods.xsl (Revision 2.03 2022/10/27)</recordOrigin>
         <languageOfCataloging>
            <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         </languageOfCataloging>
      </recordInfo>
   </originInfo>
</mods>
