<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 https://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
      version="3.4">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Simulating effects of landscape context and timber harvest on tree
                species diversity</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" usage="primary">
      <namePart type="given">Jianguo</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Liu</namePart>
      <displayForm>Liu, Jianguo</displayForm>
      <affiliation>Department of Fisheries and Wildlife, Michigan State University, East
                Lansing, Michigan 48824-1222 USA</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="given">Peter S.</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Ashton</namePart>
      <displayForm>Ashton, Peter S.</displayForm>
      <affiliation>Harvard Institute for International Development, and Department of
                Organismic and Evolutionary Biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts
                02138 USA</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <originInfo>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1999-02</dateIssued>
      <issuance>continuing</issuance>
      <language>
         <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      </language>
      <physicalDescription>
         <extent>p. 186-201.</extent>
      </physicalDescription>
      <abstract>Although the need for implementing ecosystem management across
                boundaries has been widely recognized, little is known regarding the extent to which
                loss of species richness resulting from timber harvesting in a focal forest could be
                offset by the surrounding areas. Using an individual‐based, spatially explicit
                landscape simulation model (FORMOSAIC), which considers not only the dynamics of a
                focal forest, but also the interactions between the focal forest and the neighboring
                areas, we found that tree species richness of a tropical forest was related to the
                interactions between harvest impacts and immigration from adjacent areas. Simulation
                results indicated that adjacent species‐rich forests increased species richness in a
                focal forest, but neighboring single‐species plantations had opposite effects, and
                these effects were enhanced by the duration of immigration. Heavier harvest impacts
                on residual trees resulted in lower species richness, although the negative effects
                were partially offset by immigration from species‐rich forests. Immigration after
                heavy harvest impact led to higher species richness than did immigration before
                harvesting, when the surroundings were species‐rich forests. Harvesting on the edges
                of a focal forest resulted in higher species richness than harvesting at the center
                when seed dispersal distances were short, but spatial patterns of harvesting caused
                no differences in species richness if seeds could disperse into the focal forest
                from more distant sources. Under the option of no harvest, immigration was more
                important at small spatial scales than at large spatial scales. From the
                simulations, we also noticed some unexpected results. For example, heavy harvest
                impacts reduced a higher percentage of timber species than nontimber species.
                Simulation results from this study could provide insights into identification of
                alternative methods for sustainable timber production and conservation of tree
                species richness beyond natural, management, and ownership boundaries. One potential
                method would be to establish a species‐rich seed zone around a focal forest to
                partially compensate for negative harvest impacts. Another option would be to
                harvest timber trees at optimal locations and during optimal periods of time to
                accommodate dispersal ability and availability of seeds from the
                surroundings.</abstract>
      <note>JOURNAL ARTICLE</note>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>simulation models</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>tropical forests</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>species diversity</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forest trees</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forest ecology</topic>
      </subject>
      <location>
         <physicalLocation>DNAL</physicalLocation>
      </location>
      <location>
         <url displayLabel="Available from publisher's site" usage="primary">https://dx.doi.org/10.1890/1051-0761(1999)009%5B0186:SEOLCA%5D2.0.CO;2</url>
      </location>
      <relatedItem type="host">
         <titleInfo>
            <title>Ecological applications</title>
         </titleInfo>
         <originInfo>
            <publisher>Ecological Society of America</publisher>
         </originInfo>
         <identifier type="issn"/>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl47193</identifier>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl47193</identifier>
         <part>
            <text>1999 Feb., v. 9, no. 1 p.186-201</text>
         </part>
      </relatedItem>
      <identifier type="doi">10.1890/1051-0761(1999)009[0186:SEOLCA]2.0.CO;2</identifier>
      <identifier type="control">9916299182107426</identifier>
      <identifier type="agricola">IND21979876</identifier>
      <extension>
         <identifier type="local">agid:2012631</identifier>
      </extension>
      <recordInfo>
         <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">AGL</recordContentSource>
         <recordCreationDate encoding="marc">180321</recordCreationDate>
         <recordChangeDate encoding="iso8601">20221118055817.0</recordChangeDate>
         <recordIdentifier>9916299182107426</recordIdentifier>
         <recordOrigin>Converted from MARCXML to MODS version 3.4 using NAL-RDAmarc21slim2mods.xsl (Revision 2.03 2022/10/27)</recordOrigin>
         <languageOfCataloging>
            <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         </languageOfCataloging>
      </recordInfo>
   </originInfo>
</mods>
