<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 https://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
      version="3.4">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Seed regeneration of Scots pine in boreal forest stands dominated by
                lichen and feather moss</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" usage="primary">
      <namePart type="given">Ingeborg</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Steijlen</namePart>
      <displayForm>Steijlen, Ingeborg</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="given">Marie-Charlotte</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Nilsson</namePart>
      <displayForm>Nilsson, Marie-Charlotte</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="given">Olle</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Zackrisson</namePart>
      <displayForm>Zackrisson, Olle</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="code" authority="marccountry">onc</placeTerm>
         <placeTerm type="text">Ontario</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1995-05</dateIssued>
      <issuance>continuing</issuance>
      <language>
         <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      </language>
      <physicalDescription>
         <extent>p. 713-723.</extent>
      </physicalDescription>
      <abstract>Six old-growth, late postfire Scots pine (Pinussylvestris L.)
                dominated forest stands of the Vaccinium–Cladina type were selected along a
                latitudinal gradient in northern Sweden. In two of the stands, Scots pine seedlings
                that had naturally regenerated during the last 40 years were surveyed in relation to
                field- and bottom-layer vegetation. The most abundant forest floor species, viz.
                Cladina spp., occupied 41% of the ground cover and dominated the microhabitat of
                Scots pine seedlings &lt;10 years old. The second most common species,
                Pleuroziumschreberi (Bird.) Mitt., which occupied 10 and 20% of the ground cover at
                the two sites, was, in contrast, only found to cover less than 3% of the
                microhabitat of the seedlings &lt; 10 years old. With increasing age of seedlings
                (&gt;10 years), however, the cover of Cladina spp. significantly decreased and the
                cover of P. schreberi and various ericaceous species slightly increased. Thus Scots
                pine seedlings initially establish in lichen-dominated vegetation but as they
                develop P. schreberi and ericaceous species gradually become more abundant in the
                ground vegetation. The relationships between natural establishment patterns and
                microhabitat were further empirically tested by sowing seeds of Scots pine in
                patches of Cladina spp. and patches of P. schreberi. Seeding was performed in six
                sites during 3 consecutive years. A significant higher number of established Scots
                pine seedlings were found in Cladina spp. vegetation than in P. schreberi dominated
                vegetation, and Scots pine seedlings in P. schreberi experienced a significantly
                higher mortality. Laboratory studies indicated a negative chemical influence by P.
                schreberi on Scots pine seed germination but not on radicle growth of pregerminated
                seeds. The negative influence of P. schreberi on Scots pine seed germination and
                seedling survival in the field experiments is interpreted as an effect of moisture
                factors, chemical interference, and barriers of nutrient availability. Age
                structures of naturally established Scots pine showed evidence of continuous
                regeneration over the last 40 years. The study emphasizes the importance of
                biotically mediated regeneration patterns in explaining spatial stand structure and
                temporal dynamics in northern boreal Scots pine forest ecosystems during prolonged
                absence of fire. Tree regeneration tends not to be associated with mesoscale
                characteristics such as gaps and tip-up mounds, but rather with microhabitat
                conditions. The results have implications for predicting the effect of climatic
                warming.</abstract>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Pinus sylvestris</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>boreal forests</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>natural regeneration</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>microhabitats</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Vaccinium</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>seed germination</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>mortality</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Cladonia</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <geographic>Sweden</geographic>
      </subject>
      <location>
         <physicalLocation>DNAL</physicalLocation>
      </location>
      <location>
         <url displayLabel="Available from publisher's site" usage="primary">http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/x95-079</url>
      </location>
      <relatedItem type="host">
         <titleInfo>
            <title>Canadian journal of forest research</title>
         </titleInfo>
         <originInfo>
            <publisher>NRC Research Press</publisher>
         </originInfo>
         <identifier type="issn"/>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl2003</identifier>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl2003</identifier>
         <part>
            <text>1995 May 01, v. 25, no. 5 p.713-723</text>
         </part>
      </relatedItem>
      <identifier type="doi">10.1139/x95-079</identifier>
      <identifier type="control">9916296283507426</identifier>
      <identifier type="agricola">IND20474081</identifier>
      <extension>
         <identifier type="local">agid:1405847</identifier>
      </extension>
      <recordInfo>
         <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">AGL</recordContentSource>
         <recordCreationDate encoding="marc">160807</recordCreationDate>
         <recordChangeDate encoding="iso8601">20221118110409.0</recordChangeDate>
         <recordIdentifier>9916296283507426</recordIdentifier>
         <recordOrigin>Converted from MARCXML to MODS version 3.4 using NAL-RDAmarc21slim2mods.xsl (Revision 2.03 2022/10/27)</recordOrigin>
         <languageOfCataloging>
            <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         </languageOfCataloging>
      </recordInfo>
   </originInfo>
</mods>
