<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 https://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
      version="3.4">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Does natural stand dynamics generate an aggregated pattern of canopy
                openness? A case study in Abies-Picea-Fagus old-growth forests</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" usage="primary">
      <namePart type="given">J.</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Paluch</namePart>
      <displayForm>Paluch, J.</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="given">R.</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Jastrzębski</namePart>
      <displayForm>Jastrzębski, R.</displayForm>
      <affiliation>Faculty of Forestry, University of Agriculture, Al. 29 Listopada 46,
                31–425 Krakow, Poland</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="code" authority="marccountry">xx</placeTerm>
         <placeTerm type="text">No place, unknown or undetermined</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022-03</dateIssued>
      <issuance>continuing</issuance>
      <language>
         <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      </language>
      <abstract>The action of many agents causing the mortality of overstory trees
                may potentially induce the formation of an aggregated distribution of canopy gaps.
                In this study we tested the hypothesis that natural stand dynamics generates an
                aggregated pattern of canopy openness in old-growth forests formed by Fagus
                sylvatica L., Abies alba Mill. and Picea abies (L.) H. Karst. We compared canopy
                openness and its spatial heterogeneity in five stands in the Western Carpathians
                (Central Europe) and three stands in the Dinaric Mountains (Southeast Europe). The
                stands were between 4.48 and 9.24 ha in size. In each stand we took hemispheric
                photographs in a regular 20 × 20 m grid in the leafless period to minimize coverage
                by the understory. Tree species and the dbh of live trees of dbh ≥7 cm were recorded
                on circular plots with a radius of 7 m centered at the grid points. At the stage of
                picture processing, understory trees of dbh &lt;25 cm and polar coordinates recorded
                during field measurements were removed from the pictures, and for every grid point
                the local canopy openness of the overstory layer was determined in the sky region
                defined by a zenith angle of 15°. We characterized the spatial pattern of canopy
                openness by using variograms and Moran’s I coefficients and tested the spatial
                dependence in the distribution patterns of grid points characterized by different
                levels of canopy openness. Depending on the stand, mean canopy openness varied
                between 17.5 and 41.0%, with the greatest values recorded in the Carpathian stands
                with a considerable proportion of Norway spruce and a more severe disturbance
                regime. Relationships between canopy openness and the overall number, basal area or
                volume of trees forming the overstory were strongly modified by variation in the
                density and species percentage in the mid-canopy zone. In all the stands small-scale
                variation determined for inter-point distances of 20 m accounted for the majority of
                the total variation in canopy heterogeneity and ranged between 61 and 100%. We found
                a tendency to form random patterns of canopy openness in the Dinaric stands, which
                were characterized by a greater basal area and probably also lower frequency of
                severe disturbances, and aggregated patterns in the Carpathian stands, which were
                characterized by a smaller basal area driven by more severe disturbances. The
                revealed spatial dependence in canopy openness may suggest that in the studied
                ecosystem canopy gaps are not only a legacy of the mortality of canopy trees but
                also self-organizing structural elements which, under a more severe disturbance
                regime, can affect the mortality rate in their neighbourhood. Nonetheless, the
                percentage of spatially structured variability in canopy openness observable at
                scales larger than the grid spacing used in our study was insignificant (83% on
                average). The close-to-random pattern of canopy heterogeneity may weaken the
                spatio-temporal synchronization of the juvenile growth, maturation and senescence of
                neighbouring trees and counteract the formation of coarse-grained patch
                mosaics.</abstract>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Abies alba</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Fagus sylvatica</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>Picea abies</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>administrative management</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>case studies</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>ecosystems</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>forest ecology</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>juveniles</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>mortality</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>overstory</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>spatial variation</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>trees</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <topic>understory</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <geographic>Carpathian region</geographic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <geographic>Central European region</geographic>
      </subject>
      <subject authority="atg">
         <geographic>Southern European region</geographic>
      </subject>
      <subject>
         <topic>Patch mosaic</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject>
         <topic>Developmental cycle</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject>
         <topic>Spatial pattern</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject>
         <topic>Structural diversity</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject>
         <topic>Disturbance</topic>
      </subject>
      <subject>
         <topic>Multiaged forests</topic>
      </subject>
      <location>
         <url displayLabel="Available from publisher's site" usage="primary">https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2021.119980</url>
      </location>
      <relatedItem type="host">
         <titleInfo>
            <title>Forest ecology and management</title>
         </titleInfo>
         <originInfo>
            <publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher>
         </originInfo>
         <identifier type="issn">0378-1127</identifier>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl9013</identifier>
         <identifier type="local">Journal:jnl9013</identifier>
         <part>
            <text>2022 Mar. 01, v. 507 p.119980-</text>
         </part>
      </relatedItem>
      <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.foreco.2021.119980</identifier>
      <identifier type="control">9916304622007426</identifier>
      <identifier type="agricola">IND607611503</identifier>
      <extension>
         <identifier type="local">agid:7611503</identifier>
      </extension>
      <recordInfo>
         <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">AGL</recordContentSource>
         <recordCreationDate encoding="marc">220205</recordCreationDate>
         <recordChangeDate encoding="iso8601">20221118112228.0</recordChangeDate>
         <recordIdentifier>9916304622007426</recordIdentifier>
         <recordOrigin>Converted from MARCXML to MODS version 3.4 using NAL-RDAmarc21slim2mods.xsl (Revision 2.03 2022/10/27)</recordOrigin>
         <languageOfCataloging>
            <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         </languageOfCataloging>
      </recordInfo>
   </originInfo>
</mods>
