<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 https://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
      version="3.4">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Fire ecology and management</title>
      <subTitle>past, present, and future of US forested ecosystems</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="given">Cathryn H.</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Greenberg</namePart>
      <displayForm>Greenberg, Cathryn H.</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">editor</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="date">1954-</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Beverly S.</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Collins</namePart>
      <displayForm>Collins, Beverly S.</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text">editor</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="marcgt">encyclopedia</genre>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="">Electronic books.</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
      <originInfo displayLabel="publisher">
         <place>
            <placeTerm type="text">Cham, Switzerland :Springer,2021</placeTerm>
         </place>
         <publisher>Springer</publisher>
         <dateIssued>2021</dateIssued>
      </originInfo>
      <physicalDescription>
         <form authority="marcform">print</form>
         <form authority="marccategory">electronic resource</form>
         <form authority="marcsmd">remote</form>
         <extent>1 online resource (xvii, 502 pages) : illustrations (some color).</extent>
         <form type="media" authority="rdamedia">computer</form>
         <form type="carrier" authority="rdacarrier">online resource</form>
      </physicalDescription>
      <abstract>This edited volume presents original scientific research and
                knowledge synthesis covering the past, present, and potential future fire ecology of
                major US forest types, with implications for forest management in a changing
                climate. The editors and authors highlight broad patterns among ecoregions and
                forest types, as well as detailed information for individual ecoregions, for fire
                frequencies and severities, fire effects on tree mortality and regeneration, and
                levels of fire-dependency by plant and animal communities. The foreword addresses
                emerging ecological and fire management challenges for forests, in relation to
                sustainable development goals as highlighted in recent government reports. An
                introductory chapter highlights patterns of variation in frequencies, severities,
                scales, and spatial patterns of fire across ecoregions and among forested ecosystems
                across the US in relation to climate, fuels, topography and soils, ignition sources
                (lightning or anthropogenic), and vegetation. Separate chapters by respected experts
                delve into the fire ecology of major forest types within US ecoregions, with a focus
                on the level of plant and animal fire-dependency, and the role of fire in
                maintaining forest composition and structure. The regional chapters also include
                discussion of historic natural (lightning-ignited) and anthropogenic (Native
                American; settlers) fire regimes, current fire regimes as influenced by recent
                decades of fire suppression and land use history, and fire management in relation to
                ecosystem integrity and restoration, wildfire threat, and climate change. The
                summary chapter combines the major points of each chapter, in a synthesis of US-wide
                fire ecology and forest management into the future. This book provides current,
                organized, readily accessible information for the conservation community, land
                managers, scientists, students and educators, and others interested in how fire
                behaviour and effects on structure and composition differ among ecoregions and
                forest types, and what that means for forest management today and in the future.
                .</abstract>
      <tableOfContents>Chapter 1. Introduction to Fire Ecology across USA Forested
                Ecosystems: Past, Present, and Future (Cathryn H. Greenberg, Beverly S. Collins,
                Scott Goodrick, Michael C. Stambaugh, and Gary R. Wein) -- Chapter 2. The Role of
                Fire in the Dynamics of Piedmont Vegetation (Joanna Spooner, Robert K. Peet, Michael
                P. Schafale, Alan S. Weakley and Thomas R. Wentworth) -- Chapter 3. Fire Ecology and
                Fire Management of Southeastern Coastal Plain Pine Ecosystems (Jeff S. Glitzenstein,
                J. Stephen Brewer, Ronald. E. Masters, J. Morgan Varner, and J. Kevin Hiers) --
                Chapter 4. Fire Ecology and Management in Eastern Broadleaf and Appalachian Forests
                (Mary A. Arthur, J. Morgan Varner, Charles W. Lafon, Heather D. Alexander, Daniel C.
                Dey, Craig A. Harper, Sally P. Horn, Todd F. Hutchinson, Tara L. Keyser, Marcus A.
                Lashley, Christopher E. Moorman, and Callie J. Schweitzer) -- Chapter 5. Fire
                Ecology and Management of Forest Ecosystems in the Western Central Hardwoods and
                Prairie-Forest Border (Michael C. Stambaugh, Benjamin O. Knapp, and Daniel C. Dey)
                -- Chapter 6. Fire in Floodplain Forests of the Southeastern USA hy (Paul R. Gagnon,
                Loretta L. Battaglia, Brice B. Hanberry, William H. Conner, and Sammy L. King) --
                Chapter 7. History and Future of Fire in Hardwood and Conifer Forests of the Great
                Lakes-Northeastern Forest Region, USA(Lee E. Frelich, Craig G. Lorimer, and Michael
                C. Stambaugh) -- Chapter 8. Fire Ecology of Rocky Mountain Forests(Sharon M. Hood,
                Brian J. Harvey, Paula J. Fornwalt, Cameron E. Naficy, Winslow D. Hansen, Kimberley
                T. Davis, Mike A. Battaglia, Camille Stevens-Rumann, Victoria Saab) -- Chapter 9.
                Fire Ecology of the North American Mediterranean-Climate Zone(Hugh D. Safford,
                Ramona J. Butz, Gabrielle N. Bohlman, Michelle Coppoletta, Becky L. Estes, Shana E.
                Gross, Kyle E. Merriam, Marc D. Meyer, Nicole A. Molinari, and Amarina Wuenschel) --
                Chapter 10. Fire Ecology and Management in Pacific Northwest Forests(Matthew J.
                Reilly, Jessica E. Halofsky, Meg A. Krawchuk, Daniel C. Donato, Paul F. Hessburg,
                James Johnston, Andrew Merschel, Mark E. Swanson, Joshua S. Halofsky, and Thomas A.
                Spies) -- Chapter 11. Fire Ecology and Management of Southwestern Forests(Peter Z.
                Fulé, Catrin M. Edgeley, Carol L. Chambers, Serra Hoagland, Blanca Céspedes) --
                Chapter 12. Fire and Forests in the 21st Century: Managing Resilience under Changing
                Climates and Fire Regimes in USA Forests(James M. Vose, David L. Peterson,
                Christopher J. Fettig, Jessica E. Halofsky, J. Kevin Hiers, Robert E. Keane, Rachel
                Loehman, and Michael C. Stambaugh).</tableOfContents>
      <note type="statement of responsibility" altRepGroup="00">Cathryn H</note>
      <note type="bibliography">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
      <note>Online resource; title from PDF title page (SpringerLink, viewed
                October 5, 2021).</note>
      <subject authority="lcsh">
         <topic>Forest fires</topic>
         <topic>Environmental aspects</topic>
      </subject>
      <classification authority="lcc">SD421</classification>
      <classification authority="nal">QH545.F5 F55 2021</classification>
      <location>
         <url displayLabel="SpringerLink" usage="primary">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-73267-7</url>
      </location>
      <location>
         <url displayLabel="EBSCOhost">https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;scope=site&amp;db=nlebk&amp;db=nlabk&amp;AN=3049503</url>
      </location>
      <relatedItem type="series">
         <titleInfo>
            <title>Managing forest ecosystems ; v. 39</title>
         </titleInfo>
      </relatedItem>
      <identifier type="isbn">9783030732677</identifier>
      <identifier type="isbn">3030732673</identifier>
      <identifier type="isbn" invalid="yes">9783030732660</identifier>
      <identifier type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-73267-7</identifier>
      <identifier type="control">9915461366507426</identifier>
      <identifier type="agricola">CAT31444502</identifier>
      <identifier type="oclc">1273411585</identifier>
      <extension>
         <note type="saleTape">20211027 00000000 00000000</note>
         <note type="publicationSource">Non-US</note>
      </extension>
      <recordInfo>
         <descriptionStandard>rda pn</descriptionStandard>
         <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">GW5XE</recordContentSource>
         <recordCreationDate encoding="marc">211005</recordCreationDate>
         <recordChangeDate encoding="iso8601">20221101232430.0</recordChangeDate>
         <recordIdentifier>9915461366507426</recordIdentifier>
         <recordOrigin>Converted from MARCXML to MODS version 3.4 using NAL-RDAmarc21slim2mods.xsl (Revision 2.03 2022/10/27)</recordOrigin>
         <languageOfCataloging>
            <languageTerm authority="iso639-2b" type="code">eng</languageTerm>
         </languageOfCataloging>
      </recordInfo>
   </originInfo>
</mods>
